Welcome to 2026 release wave two launch
edition. This video is about a
completely new cool thing in document
reporting called composite layouts.
So, I want to cover what this thing is
and then how you set what we called
themes and header footer layouts, how
you manage them
and
very sad if you want to turn it off, you
can do it at least for now. I'll show
you that as well.
So, what is this thing?
Basically, we allow you now
to
reuse branding like report themes,
colors,
fonts and so on
across your document reports as well as
doing the same for the header footer
layouts. So, you just define them once
and apply them everywhere.
So, the idea with composite layouts is
that
that we split kind of the old layout
would be everything all in once in one
file.
Um but now we have the middle part here,
a body layout is the structural
uh report layout for the report. Not
styled anyway, just like what is the I
want to show.
And then you can apply a theme which
adds the
the look and feel, the colors, fonts and
so on. And you can also apply a header
footer to the layout
so that you control kind of what is
shown on the headers and footers.
And applying here means it happens at
runtime. So, you can actually have the
same report um you can run it in
different ways. Um you don't have to
care about headers and footers and
themes.
You can just focus on the core thing
with a body layout.
Here's an example. So, here I have
a report layout that consists of it can
see in the top here
something that comes from the header
footer,
something that is specific for the
report for the layout,
and then a theme that is applied
that can that theme can be shared
across.
Here, let me show how it works inside
the report layouts. Here's an example of
an inventory order details. You can see
that there is
something called a body layout, right?
So, that's something that you specify
this is body layout. It is supposed to
have a header footer applied and
supposed to have a theme applied.
The actual structural body layout looks
super boring, right? There's no fancy
fonts or colors or anything. It's just
the raw structure.
And you can run that report if you want
to and then when if you do that, the the
report will render like this.
But again, there will be no header and
and no theming applied.
So, this How do you set that?
Well, you can do it in multiple ways. On
the specific layout, if you want to test
things,
you can uh
when you are on a body layout in the
menu here for report layouts, there's a
composite
layout menu where you set where you can
set the report theme and header footer.
If you do that in this example here, we
are choosing the internal default
header footer and the theme is the calm
theme. And when we apply that and run
the report, now the magic happens. We
get the header footer and we get the
calm theme applied. In this case the
calm theme is
uh with some green
to calm you down, I guess.
But, now we have reusability.
You can actually
default your organizational
uh branding basically one place if you
want to globally.
You can specify the default theme and
header footer layout like on a global
level.
For a specific company, maybe your
Danish company has one branding and the
Swedish one has another one.
You can set it on a specific report for
all the layouts or a specific layout
that I just showed you there.
This happens on the report defaults for
theme and header and footer. This
example here, you can see the global for
all the reports has a standard header
and footer and standard theme.
Um
the next line is showing how those
defaults are set on the on the Cronus
USA, so that will override the global
defaults.
Then on the inventory details report
level, there's a setting there for that
overrides the company one. And then for
the specific body layouts, um you can
you can override the report settings.
Now, we ship and I'll show you what we
ship, a number of these themes and
header and footer layouts, but you can
also add your own. That's actually the
whole idea here is that if you want to
brand things your way,
um
you can add your own themes and header
and footer layouts either in the
application on for from AL code.
In the application, it is coming from
the managed theme and header and footer
layouts page where you can simply do a
new theme or a new header and footer
layout.
And you can add in this case
a header and footer, give it a name, a
description. You can create a blank
layout or you can upload an existing
one.
Um if you do it from AL, here is what
you need in the rendering section. You
need to specify for a theme at dot x
file because we're using uh
word templates dot that's the T in dot.
Uh you need to specify word and the
subtype would be a theme.
Whereas if you add a header footer
layout from uh from AL,
it's still subtype word or sorry, type
word, but the subtype will be header
footer. And you saw previously in the
video that for the body layouts, they
have subtype body.
Now,
from uh the product group, we aim to
ship in version 20.9 and 20.1 and send
20.9.1
um three themes,
approximately eight um header footer
layouts, and give or take 50 different
body layouts across different functional
areas.
Mainly in the beginning here so that you
can try it out and and get a feeling for
it. Also, if you want to do this on your
own report objects, there are samples uh
here that you can where you can see how
it works.
Um here's just uh some some of the
some of the themes that we have calm,
default, playful, and a standard theme.
And for header footer layouts, we have
divided them into external and internal
reports. For external, it's typically
the ones you send out where you want
your logo. Internal reports are
typically things that you want on PDF or
paper, but you just want minimal things.
Maybe it's just a very simple header. No
don't want to waste any anything um to
put the logo on those.
All right.
But shouldn't we see this in action? I
maybe I should have started with that,
but here we are.
Um I have um one of the reports that I
think really illustrates um the change.
Which is the customer statement.
To the left you can see the old layout
that shipped in Business Central or
ships with Business Central. There is
this blue table, the logo and so on.
And to the right you see the new body
layout with the default header footer
and default theme applied.
And if you ask me, I think the new
report looks just more much more sleek.
But that's just one combination of theme
and
header footers, right?
So what if we instead try to illustrate
the same body layout, same header
footer, but now applying some different
themes. So here you see the default
theme on the left. You see the calm
theme in the middle.
And a little what we call playful, which
is add some colors and pink and what
have you as a radiant as well. If if
that's something that that you think
would look good on your invoices.
Now this is just different ways of
branding. You can of course add your .x
branding and then it would look like
your company letter head.
Here's an example where
I'm taking the same body layout, three
different header footer layouts instead.
I'm just using the same theme. You can
see the customer statement in different
ways with different representation of
that header footer layout.
Or you could just mix and match. I mean,
right now I have
one body, three themes and I think eight
different header footers. I mean,
there's many combinations. So here's the
default default, calm modern and playful
detailed application. But they're still
just one body layout. I think that's
pretty cool.
Okay.
How can you roll out to your
organization? Well,
you can use feature management, you can
use layout status, and
remark that we are not changing any
default states or states for for any of
the layouts we ship in in in in here in
version 2026.
So, it's not that when you update to the
to the next major here, that suddenly
your invoices will look completely
different. We're not touching the
default state at all. So, you can You
should be able to roll this out in a
completely risk-free way.
Okay, so I'm using just the advanced
tell me searching here for how can we
roll out composite layouts in our
organization.
This is using semantic search. I'm just
searching for that in advanced tell me,
and it tells me that I can use feature
management as the first link. And on
feature management, there's a way to
enable or turn off
this new
what we call document experience.
So, I mean,
you can you can gradually roll it out
on different environments,
but you can also gradually roll it out
on layouts. Because one of the new
features, that's actually a different
video, look at
the description here to get a link for
that. We have the ability for you to
set the state status of even the the
layouts we ship to to either retired or
draft. In this case here, I have taken
the financial report landscape layout,
and I'm setting that pending approval as
the state, even though it's a layout
shipped by Microsoft. And that means
that no user will be able to use
this layout when they run reports. This
layout will not show up on the request
page. It only shows up here in the
report layout page.
That's it. Long video, but also super
cool new feature. There's only one more
thing before we end this, and that is if
you want to learn more,
there is an AKA link for our developer
documentation, AKA.ms/BCdeveloper.
It takes you
to a landing page. Scroll down to find
the report part of that, and learn
everything there is to composite
layouts, the new way we envision
document reports for Business Central.
Thanks for watching. Hope you have a
great launch edition with other things
to learn. This video is over. Have a
great day. Bye.